Guide to the Baker-Ripley Foundation Records MS 728
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
Baker-Ripley Foundation Records
1924-2010
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Baker-Ripley Foundation
MS 728
8.75 Linear Feet 9 boxes
The Baker-Ripley Foundation records document the history and on-going operations of the Foundation through meetings and financial reports, property, legal and administration records.
Biographical / Historical
In 1934 Mrs. Edith Hudson Ripley's will provided bequests to endow the Daniel and Edith Ripley Foundation. Pursuing the Ripley's goal of general benevolence in memory of her and her late husband, the Foundation's directors made a major gift in 1938 to the Houston Settlement Association that planned for the original Ripley House, constructed for Houston Settlement Association's use. The Foundation bought land and constructed Kirkland-Ripley 1950-51, Tsanoff-Ripley ca. 1972, Cleveland-Ripley 1968, Harbach-Ripley 1958-62. Numerous facilities and land, repairs, enhancements and renovations, and programs soon followed. Houston Settlement Association/Neighborhood Centers, Inc. eventually merged with Ripley House. The adopted mission of the Daniel and Edith Ripley Foundation is "to be a memorial of general benevolence to the memory of Daniel Ripley and Edith Ripley, his wife, by establishing, supporting, maintaining and operating in the Houston area major buildings and grounds to be used exclusively for charitable and educational purposes, and generally to carry out any other activity in connnection with the foregoing."
Scope and Contents
The collection of Baker-Ripley Foundation records chronciles the existence of the Houston Settlement Association/Neighborhood Centers, Inc. with Ripley House and their subsequent merger through its business records that include organizational/historical, financial, meetings, property and building-related, legal and administrative holdings.
Conditions Governing Access
This material is open for research.
Stored off-site at the Library Service Center. Please request this material via woodson@rice.edu or call 713-348-2586.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The papers were donated by Baker-Ripley Foundation, James Greenwood III Chief Executive Officer, and Kate Birenbaum, General Counsel and Vice President of Governance on Dec. 11, 2017.
Arrangement
The materials in this collection have been arragned in seven series as follows: Series I: Organizational/historical Series II: Meetings Series III: Property and building-related Series IV: Financial Series V: Legal Series VI: Administrative Series VIII: Sheltering Arms
Index Terms
Subjects
Business
- Series I: Organizational/Historical
  - Daniel Ripley estate, 1921-1922 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Rice Institute Ripley scholarships, 1927-1928 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Edith Ripley's will, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Edith Ripley estate: probate records, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Daniel and Edith Ripley Foundation charter, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Articles of Incorporation, 1935-2007 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Trust instrument, 194? (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Sub-series A: Ripley Foundation
    - Establishment, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Franklin I. Harbach biographical sketch (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Historical background (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - New Ripley House dedication/groundbreaking, 1999-07-01 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - New Ripley House opening, 2001-04 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Neighborhood Centers Inc. history project, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - NCI 100th anniversary, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 14-15)
  - Ripley House 75th anniversary, 2015 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Historical background (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Neighborhood Centers Association history: Neighborhood Doorways, by Corrinne S. Tsanoff (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Mission statement (Box 1, Folder 19-20)
  - Non-profit status (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Bylaws: original, amended, revised (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Daniel and Edith Ripley Foundation building photo (Drawer 35)
- Series II: Meetings
  - Sub-series A: Board of Directors
    - 1935-1939 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - 1940-1949 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - 1950-1959 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - 1960- (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - 1970-1979 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Minute book of Trustees, 1935-1985 (Box 1)
    - Minute book of Trustees, 1980-1990 (Box 1)
    - Minute book, 1992-04-22-1997-04-09 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - 1998 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - 1999 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - 2001 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Executive, 1995-1997 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Sub-series B: Special
    - 1998-01-12 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - 2000-11-15 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - 2000-11-22 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - 2002 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - 2003 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - re: Cleveland-Ripley, 2005-03-30 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - 2005-07-19 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - 2005-08-08 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - 2005-12-21 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - 2007-01-31 (Box 2, Box 15)
    - 2007-10-01 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Sub-series C: Annual
    - 1998 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - 1999 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - 2000 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - 2001 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - 2002 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - 2003 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - 2004 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - 2005 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - 2006 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - 2007 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - 2008 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - 2009 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - 2010 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - 2011 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - 2012 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - 2013 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - 2014 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - 2015 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - 2016 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Series III: Property and building-related
  - Sub-series A: Surveys
    - Ripley House complex land title survey (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Ripley House complex construction surveys (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Lovejoy Ave. property, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Cleveland-Ripley, 2004 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Ripley House subdivision plat, 2000 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Asbestos, 2006 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Navigation Blvd. properties (4406/4418) (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Clinic footprint, 2000 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Sub-series B: Construction/improvements
    - Renovation ad hoc committee, 1995 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Building replacement, 1996-1999 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Existing stonework/friezes, 2000 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Images, 2000 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Marquee, 2002 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Mural project, 2002, 2012-2013 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Softball field barrier netting, 2003 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Artificial turf field and scoreboard, 2004 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Boys and Girls Clubs of Greater Houston, Inc., 2004 (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Boys and Girls Clubs of Greater Houston, Inc. signage, 2004 (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - Cleveland-Ripley Community Center renovations, 2005 (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - 4410 Navigation Blvd. improvements, 2005-2006, 2013-2014 (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - Exterior work testing, 2006 (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - Playground equipment Harbach-Ripley Community Center, 2006 (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - Playground fitness equipment, 2006 (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - Structural reports, 2014 (Box 3, Folder 30)
    - Playground equipment Cleveland-Ripley Community Center, 2008 (Box 3, Folder 31)
    - Harbach-Ripley renovations, 2010-2016 (Box 3, Folder 32)
    - Tsanoff-Ripley Middle School construction project, 2011 (Box 3, Folder 33)
    - Tsanoff-Ripley Charter Middle School renovations, 2011-2013 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Tsanoff-Ripley signage, 2012 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - BBQ pit, 2012 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Curb cut/ramp, 2012 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Solar generator, 2012 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Fruit tree planting, 2013 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - North wing, 2013-2014 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Cleveland-Ripley Community Center renovations, 2016 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Sub-series C: Maintenance
    - Waste and storm drainage (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Waste water pollution prevention (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Asbestos operations and maintenance program, 2000, 2004 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Trees and drains, 2003 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Exterior, 2006 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Distress problem repairs, 2007, 2012, 2014 (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Piezometer measuring, 2008 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Piezometer readings-soil testing, 2009 (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - Piezometer readings and water levels, 2010-2011 (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - Interior and exterior work, 2010-2016 (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - Ceiling (Box 4, Folder 19)
- Series IV: Financial
  - Sub-series A: General
    - Request to IRS for 'set aside' option of funds for Ripley House construction, 1996-1997 (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - Kirkland-Ripley, 1998-2009 (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - Cash flow budget, 1998-2010 (Box 4, Folder 22)
    - Rent for facilities, 2001 (Box 4, Folder 23)
    - Actions, 2005 (Box 4, Folder 24)
    - Cleveland-Ripley budget, 2005-2007 (Box 4, Folder 25)
    - Cleveland-Ripley fundraising, 2007 (Box 4, Folder 26)
    - Vanguard opening accounts, 2007-2008 (Box 4, Folder 27)
    - Amegy Bank, 2008 (Box 4, Folder 28)
    - Vanguard bills paid, 2008-2015 (Box 4, Folder 29)
    - Vanguard statements, 2008-2016 (Box 4, Folder 30-31)
    - NCI restricted funds, 2008-2016 (Box 4, Folder 32)
    - Amegy Bank statements, 2009-2017 (Box 4, Folder 33)
    - "Heart of Gold" celebrations, 2010 (Box 4, Folder 34)
    - Finance Cmte., 2010 (Box 4, Folder 35)
    - Vanguard change of ownership, 2010-2016 (Box 4, Folder 36)
    - Reinstatement to non-profit status, 2010, 2014 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Investment Cmte., 2013 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Support organizations, 2013-2014 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Capital fund campaign, 2015 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Vanguard resolutions, 2016 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - NCI TD Industries, 2016 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Sub-series B: Taxes
    - Property tax exemption (Box 5, Folder 7-8)
    - Sales tax exemption (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Exemption and payment-Bering Street tract, 2006 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Protest hearing-Bering Street tract, 2004 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Exemptions and delinquencies (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Certificates-H.I.S.D., 1999 (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - Certificates-County, 1998-1999 (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - Distribution requirements, 2015-2016 (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - Distribution carryover (Box 5, Folder 16)
    - HCAD, 2014 (Box 5, Folder 17)
    - Set-aside fund (Box 5, Folder 18)
    - Annual tax filings
      - 1996 (Box 5, Folder 19)
      - 1997 (Box 5, Folder 20)
      - 1998 (Box 5, Folder 21)
      - 2000 (Box 5, Folder 22)
      - 2001 (Box 5, Folder 23)
      - 2003 (Box 5, Folder 24)
      - 2004 (Box 5, Folder 25)
      - 2005 (Box 5, Folder 26)
      - 2006 (Box 5, Folder 27)
      - 2007 (Box 5, Folder 28)
      - 2008 (Box 5, Folder 29)
      - 2009 (Box 5, Folder 30)
      - 2010 (Box 5, Folder 31)
      - 2011 (Box 5, Folder 32)
      - 2012 (Box 5, Folder 33)
      - 2013 (Box 5, Folder 34)
      - 2014 (Box 5, Folder 35)
      - 2015 (Box 5, Folder 36)
      - 2016 (Box 6, Folder 1)
- Series V: Legal
  - Sub-series A: General
    - Deeds 4401 Lovejoy St., 1938 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Deed 2411 Canal, Rusk Settlement, 1947, 1950, 1963 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Deed Harbach-Ripley building (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Deed and survey Cleveland-Ripley building, 1960, 1965 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - City of Pasadena acreage purchase from Ripley, 1965, 1970-71, 1974 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Deed Highland Acres, Pasadena TX, 1970-1971 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - "Set-aside" ruling application, 1995-1997 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Property acquisition 4418 Navigation Blvd., 1997 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Trademark matters (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Land acquisition west and north sides of campus, 1999 (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - Land acquisition C.T. Allen tracts, 1999 (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - Land acquisition 4402 Navigation Blvd., 1999 (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - Sanitary sewer easement, 1999-2000 (Box 6, Folder 14)
    - Land acquisition 328 N. Sidney, 1999 (Box 6, Folder 15)
    - Parking lot at Navigation Blvd., 2000-2001 (Box 6, Folder 16)
    - Bering Street "stub" abandonment, 2002-2004 (Box 6, Folder 17)
    - Variance request, Blantyre Homes at McAlpine St., 2004 (Box 6, Folder 18)
    - Asbestos abatement, 2004-2006 (Box 6, Folder 19)
    - NCI distress problem settlement, 2006 (Box 6, Folder 20)
    - JP Morgan separation, 2007-2008 (Box 6, Folder 21)
    - Electric Vehicle Supply Equipment (EVSE) agreement, 2013 (Box 6, Folder 22)
    - Merger of Ripley Foundation with Neighborhood Centers, Inc., 2017 (Box 6, Folder 23)
    - Merger final, 2017 (Box 6, Folder 24)
  - Sub-series B: Insurance
    - Commitment for title insurance on properties, 1999, 2005 (Box 6, Folder 25)
    - NCI, 2000-2017 (Box 6, Folder 26)
    - NCI issues, 2005-2006 (Box 6, Folder 27)
    - Directors and officers liability
      - 2012-2013 (Box 6, Folder 28)
      - 2013-2014 (Box 6, Folder 29)
      - 2014-2015 (Box 6, Folder 30)
      - 2015-2016 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Commercial (Travelers), 2015-2016 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Commercial excess liability, 2015-2016 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Sub-series C: Leases/sub-leases
    - Ripley/NCI, 1984 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Ripley/NCI, 1994-1996 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Ripley-NCI; Tsanoff-Ripley; sublease to Mental Health and Mental Retardation Authority; Kirkland; Harbach (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Ripley/NCI, 1995-04-1995-06 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Ripley/NCI, 1995-12 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - KIrkland-Ripley/NCI/Boys and Girls Club of Greater Houston, 1995, 2015-2016 (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - Ripley/NCI/Harris County Hospital District, 1996 (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - Ripley/NCI (original), 2000 (Box 7, Folder 11)
    - Ripley/NCI, 2000 (Box 7, Folder 12)
    - NCI/Ripley/Tsanoff-Ripley Community Center, 2001 (Box 7, Folder 13)
    - Ripley/NCI/Mexican American Legal Defense and Educational Fund, 2001 (Box 7, Folder 14)
    - Ripley/NCI/Mental Health and Mental Retardation Authority of Harris County, 2001 (Box 7, Folder 15)
    - Ripley-NCI/Tsanoff-Ripley building (with amendment), 2001, 2003 (Box 7, Folder 16)
    - Ripley/NCI/Texas Children's Pediatrics Associates, 2002-2003 (Box 7, Folder 17)
    - Krikland-Ripley/NCI/Boys and Girls Club of Greater Houston, 2003 (Box 7, Folder 18)
    - Ripley/NCI/Council on Alcohol and Drugs Houston, 2003 (Box 7, Folder 19)
    - Ripley/NCI/Ambassador's International Ballet Folklorico, 2004 (Box 7, Folder 20)
    - Ripley-NCI/Tsanoff-Ripley/Kirkland-Ripley/Harbach-Ripley/Cleveland-Ripley, 2004-2005 (Box 7, Folder 21)
    - Ripley-NCI/ Tsanoff-Ripley building, 2005 (Box 7, Folder 22)
    - Ripley/NCI, 2005 (Box 7, Folder 23)
    - Ripley-NCI/Cleveland-Ripley amendment, 2005 (Box 7, Folder 24)
    - Ripley-NCI /Cleveland-Ripley Community Center, 2005 (Box 7, Folder 25)
    - Tenants (sub-leasees), as of July 2005 (Box 7, Folder 26)
    - Ripley/NCI for Kirkland and Harbach buildings, 2005-2006 (Box 7, Folder 27)
    - Kirkland-Ripley/NCI/Boys and Girls Clubs of Greater Houston, 2006, 2011-13 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Ripley/City of Houston HPD Storefront, 2008 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Ripley-NCI/Tsanoff-Ripley building, 2011 (Box 8, Folder 3-4)
    - Ripley-NCI/Ambassador's International Ballet Folklorico, 2012 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Terms, 2014 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Ripley/NCI/Texas Children's Pediatrics, 2015 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Ripley-Boys and Girls Club of Greater Houston, 2015-2016 (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - Ripley-NCI/Cleveland-Ripley amendment, 2016 (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - Ripley/NCI/Parris Foundation, 2016 (Box 8, Folder 10)
- Series VI: Administrative
  - General business
    - 1986-1993 (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - 1990-1993 (Box 8, Folder 12)
    - 1994-1995 (Box 8, Folder 13)
    - 1996 (Box 8, Folder 14)
    - 1997 (Box 8, Folder 15)
    - 2016 (Box 8, Folder 16)
  - Case statement for rebuilding Ripley House, ca. 1995 (Box 8, Folder 17)
  - Jim Greenwood employment, 1997 (Box 8, Folder 18)
  - NCI relationship history, 1997, 2001, 2003-04 (Box 8, Folder 19)
  - NCI new model, 2006 (Box 8, Folder 20)
  - Foundation pledge, 2007-11, 2014 (Box 8, Folder 21)
  - Application for water/wastewater services, 2011 (Box 8, Folder 22)
  - Buescher and Friedrichs memorials, 2012 (Box 8, Folder 23)
  - NCI Director, 2013-2016 (Box 8, Folder 24)
  - NCI general report, 2015 (Box 8, Folder 25)
  - Appraisal report for Kirkland-Ripley, 2016-11-21 (Box 8, Folder 26)
  - Property deeds digest (Box 8, Folder 27)
  - "Heart of Gold" celebration
    - 1998-2001, 2003-2004 (Box 8, Folder 28)
    - 2008-2009 (Box 8, Folder 29)
    - 2014-2016 (Box 8, Folder 30)
- Series VII: Sheltering Arms
  - Sub-series A: Folio
    - Letter from Rt. Rev. Henry D. Aves to Mrs. Head, Secretary Sheltering Arms, 1925-01-23 (Box 9)
    - Charter [copy] of Sheltering Arms, 1893-05-12 (Box 9)
    - From Mrs. A.E. Schaeffer to President and members of Sheltering Arms re: minutes of commissioner's county court, 1897-03-16 (Box 9)
    - Constitution and By-Laws of The Sheltering Arms (Box 9)
    - Revised By-Laws of Sheltering Arms Corporation, 1957-11 (Box 9)
    - Letter from Isabella M. Schaeffer to Mrs. Head, 1928-08-17 (Box 9)
    - Letter from Board of Sheltering Arms to Rev. Sears, 1911-11-25 (Box 9)
    - Note from Winifred Hirsch to Board and staff of Sheltering Arms, 1983-12 (Box 9)
    - Letter from Emily (Mrs. J.W.) Evans to Mrs. Schaeffer, 1924-10-22 (Box 9)
    - Letter from C.F. Forsyth to Mrs. J.M. Head, 1925-01-14 (Box 9)
    - Letter from Mrs. Ella Tripp to Mrs. Head, 1925-01-23 (Box 9)
    - Letter from W.B. Chew to Mrs. J.J. Clemens (Box 9)
    - Letter from Margaret W. Brooks to Mrs. Head, 1924-11-02 (Box 9)
    - Memorial listings (Box 9)
    - Letter from I.M. Wilford to Mrs. Hines, 1941-11-03 (Box 9)
    - Letter from Sheltering Arms Association Board to vestrymen of Christ Church (Box 9)
    - Letter from C.F. Forsyth to Mrs. Head, 1924-10-28 (Box 9)
    - Letter from Sterling Myer to Mrs.W.C. Crane, 1912-06-06 (Box 9)
    - Consent from Rector P.G. Sears, 1906-03-07 (Box 9)
  - Sub-series B: Ledger, binders
    - Ledger of residents information, 1937-11-01 (Box 9)
    - Binder with resident information and newsclips (Box 9)
    - Binder with resident information, 1927 (Box 9)